Finding Aid for the William R. Day Collection day
William R. Day Collection
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
William R. Day Collection
1788 1942
1788-1942
day
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
1.5 Linear Feet
1 record center box; 1 flat storage box (medium)
The bulk of the William R. Day Collection concerns the life and work of William Rufus Day. There are also materials related to other immediate and extended family members. Some of the topics covered in the William R. Day Collection are the Spanish-American War; the United States Peace Commission; the Mixed Claim Commission concerning reparations from Berlin, Germany; and William Day's career as a lawyer and diplomat. Materials represented include correspondence, newspaper clippings, publications, and manuscripts.
Day, Luther
Day, William R., (William Rufus), 1849-1923
Scope and Contents note
This collection contains a variety of materials including correspondence, newspaper clippings, publications, and manuscripts. Although the bulk of the collection concerns William Rufus Day, there are materials related to other immediate and extended family members. Some of the topics covered in the William R. Day Collection are the Spanish-American War; the United States Peace Commission; the Mixed Claim Commission concerning reparations from Berlin, Germany; and William Day's career.
The Correspondence and Papers series consists of 3 subseries: William Day, Family, and Miscellaneous.
The William Day subseries is organized by date and includes correspondence related to the Spanish-American War, Cuba, Germany and the Mixed Claims Commission. In 1896 there are materials related to the Monroe Doctrine, silver and gold, and Venezuela and Cuba. The 1897 folder primarily has correspondence related to Spain and Cuba. The 1898 folder contains materials related to Cuba, Spain, Germany, Puerto Rico, and the Philippines. The 1899 folder contains congratulations William Day received upon being appointed a judgeship as well as speaking requests. 1900-1911 contains remarks, information about a Day family land transfer, Day's McKinley manuscript, a map of Washington, DC, and a European military map. 1920-1923 has correspondence and papers related to the 18th amendment (prohibition), the Berlin agreement by the Mixed Claims Commission, and Day's retirement from the Commission. Biographical materials include biographies, a genealogy, ancestry from the Mayflower, and a memorial. The scrapbook contains newspaper clippings related to William Day's work and life as well as that of his wife, Mary Elizabeth Schaefer, and his son, Luther Day. Topics are related to William Day's political and judicial career including the Spanish-American War, Cuba, and the Philippines, and Luther Days' career as a lawyer and politician.
The subseries Family includes four files. The folder for Luther Day, father of William R. Day, contains correspondence to Luther as well as papers related to him being elected a prosecuting attorney. The folder for Emily Spalding Day, mother of William R. Day, contains letters from her mother, sister, and cousin, as well as one letter from Emily to her mother. The folder for Louis Schaefer, father-in-law of William R. Day, contains letters to Louis from members of the Meiklehaus family and one letter from Louis Schaefer to his daughter on Schaefer's Opera House stationary. The Other Members folder contains letters and papers for other members of the Day family including Ellen Day, Laura Lyman, Frances Day, Lucretia Spalding, Honorable Spalding, Ida Barker, Luther Day (William R Day's son), Asa Spalding, and a pamphlet titled Industrial Peace with Justice which lists Stephen A. Day as the president.
The three miscellaneous folders contain papers and letters whose relationship to the Day family and William R. Day is unknown including a letter written in 1797 by Darius Morgan, a letter from 1795 to Ephraim Root, as well as some additional letters, a memo about being an officer of the United States, information relating to the Hero of Bitche, Red Cross instructions for knitting socks, and a list of names.
The Manuscripts series contains William Day's notebook related to his biographical project on William McKinley, Stephen Day's (William Day's son) notebook related to sales and cases he worked on, the dissertation of Joseph McLean about William Rufus Day submitted to New York University, and a folder of miscellaneous materials including a review of a German newspaper and an incomplete document about patent law and the rights of inventors.
The Newspaper series includes issues of the University of Michigan newspaper The Chronicle from 1868-1870 and an assortment of newspaper clippings from 1894-1950.
The Publications series brings together the published materials within the William Day Collection. They are mostly political in nature and relate to law cases, government documents and procedures, and political opinions. Also included are speeches given by William R. Day.
The Ephemera folder contains two items. One is an envelope for Goldie's Pens that begins "This packet contains as assortment (10) of the Goldie's, the highest grade of writing pens..." There is also a photograph of Robbie Hubbs on the packaging. Inside the envelope is a tissue that contains some unidentified seeds. The other item in the Ephemera folder is a carte de visite printed by Brand Artist. The portrait is undated and the subject unidentified, but it may be a young William R. Day.
Biographical/Historical note
William Rufus Day was an American diplomat and lawyer. He was born in Ohio on April 17, 1849, and he died in Michigan on July 9, 1923. In 1870 he graduated from the University of Michigan with a Bachelor of Science degree, after which he took classes at the University of Michigan Law School. He entered the bar in 1872, and began a law partnership in Canton, Ohio. Day was appointed to the position of Assistant Secretary of State by William McKinley in 1897. In 1898, Day was named Secretary of State, although he left the position quickly in order to lead the United States Peace Commission to help negotiate the end of the Spanish-American war. In 1999, McKinley appointed him to a seat on the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit. In 1903 Theodore Roosevelt named Day an Associate Justice of the United States Supreme Court, and Day served on the Supreme Court until he retired in 1922. In 1922 President Harding appointed Day the Umpire of the Mixed Claims Commission between the United States and Berlin. Day was also a writer and some of his speeches were published. His writings include works on President McKinley and a number of important legal opinions.
Conditions Governing Access note
The collection is open for research.
Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Newspaper clippings.; Scrapbooks.; Spain. |t Treaties, etc. |g United States, |d 1898 December 10; Spanish-American War, 1898; Day, Luther, 1813-1885; McKinley, William, 1843-1901; Mixed Claims Commission, United States and Germany.
- Correspondence and Papers
  Scope and Contents note
  The Correspondence and Papers series contains correspondence and papers from William Day and various family members.
  - William Day, 1896 1923; 1896-1923
    - 1896, 1896 1896 (Box 1)
    - 1897, 1897 1897 (Box 1)
    - 1898 (3 folders), 1898 1898 (Box 1)
    - 1899, 1899 1899 (Box 1)
    - 1900-1911 (Box 1)
    - 1920-1923 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - Biographical (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook (Box 2)
  - Family
    - Luther Day (Father), 1844 1884; 1844-1884 (Box 1)
    - Emily Spalding Day (Mother), 1840 1884; 1840-1884 (Box 1)
    - Louis Schaefer (Father-in-Law) (Box 1)
    - Other Members (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (3 folders) (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  The Manuscripts series contains work by William Day and his son, Stephen Day. It also has a dissertation about William Day by Joseph McLean, and a folder of miscellaneous materials.
  - William Day on McKinley (Box 1)
  - Stephan Day Notebook (Box 1)
  - McLean Dissertation on William Day (2 folders), 1942 1942; 1942 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Newspapers
  The Newspaper series includes issues of the University of Michigan newspaper The Chronicle from 1868-1870 and an assortment of newspaper clippings from 1894-1950.
  - The Chronicle University of Michigan, 1868 1870; 1868-1870 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1894 1950; 1894-1950 (Box 1)
- Publications
  The Publications series brings together the published materials within the William R. Day Collection, including some of his speeches.
  - Supreme Court Booklets (2 folders)
    - Rules of the Supreme Court of the United States 1916, 1916 1916 (Box 1)
    - Supreme Court Reporter Vol. 43 No. 13 1923, 1923 1923 (Box 1)
    - Supreme Court of the United States No. 1311 C. E. Cook, O. J. Cook, Cyrus Frease, J. B. Chamerlain, John Jackson, and J. Lawrence, versus the United States (2 copies), 1890 1890; 1890 (Box 1)
    - Supreme Court of the United States October 16, 1922, 1922 1922 (Box 1)
    - Supreme Court of the United States October 3, 1922, 1922 1922 (Box 1)
    - Supreme Court of the United States Eben Newton et als versus the Board of County Commissioners of Mahnoning County, Ohio (Box 1)
    - Supreme Court of the United States Eber B. Ward et al versus Philo Chamberline et al, 1862 1862; 1862 (Box 1)
    - List of Works Relating to the Supreme Court of the United States 1909, 1909 1909 (Box 1)
  - House of Representatives Booklets
    - Forty-Eighth Congress Jonathan H. Wallace vs William McKinley, Jr (2 copies) (Box 1)
    - H. R. 12704 - appropriation act, 1922 1922; 1922 (Box 1)
    - Expenses of Mixed Claims Commission, United States and Germany, 1922 1922; 1922 (Box 1)
  - Treaties
    - Treaty series number 659 between the United States and Austria, 1921 1921; 1921 (Box 1)
    - Treaty series 665 between the United States and Germany, 1922 1922; 1922 (Box 1)
    - Papers Relating to the Treaty with Spain, 1901 1901; 1901 (Box 1)
  - Ohio Booklets
    - Biographical Sketches of the Fifty-Sixth Ohio Senate, 1864 1864; 1864 (Box 1)
    - Supreme Court of Ohio Richard H. Umbenhour vs The State of Ohio (Box 1)
  - Speeches and Writings by William Day
    - Address of William R. Day at the Ravenna, Ohio Homecoming, August 25, 1909 (2 copies), 1909 1909 (Box 1)
    - Our Place in the International Family, 1901 1901; 1901 (Box 1)
    - Address of William R. Day at the Conference under the auspices of the American Peace Centenary Committee, held at Makinac Island July 21, 22, 1914, 1914 1914 (Box 1)
    - Address of William R. Day at the Unveiling of the Marquette Statue on Mackinac Island, September 1, 1909 (2 copies), 1909 1909 (Box 1)
    - Remarks of William R. Day at the dinner in honor of John Joy Edson on this seventy-fifth birthday, May 17, 1921 (2 copies), 1921 1921 (Box 1)
    - Testimonial to John Joy Edson by his Friends and Fellow-Citizens, 1921 1921; 1921 (Box 1)
    - Sophomore Exhibition program Class of 1870, 1868 1868; 1868 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Booklets
    - Diplomatic List Department of State April, 1923, 1923 1923 (Box 1)
    - Mary B. Barber: An Appreciation by Luther Day, 1917 1917; 1917 (Box 1)
    - The Record of the Assocation of the Bar of the City of New York, December 1848, 1848 1848 (Box 1)
    - McKinley as a Diplomatist by John Bassett Moore, 1914 1914; 1914 (Box 1)
    - Americanism addresses by Woodrow Wilson, Franklin K. Lane, Theodore Roosevelt (Box 1)
    - The Autobiography of Abraham Lincoln (Box 1)
    - John Adams Inaugural Address (Box 1)
    - A Message to Garcia by Elbert Hubbard (Box 1)
    - The Man Without a Country by Edward Everett Hale (Box 1)
- Ephemera
  The Ephemera series contains a carte de visite and a packet of seeds.
  - Envelope for Goldie's Pens: Contains seeds. (Box 1)
  - Carte de Visite of William R. Day (?) (Box 1)